So we've got the National Assembly, which is the conflation of what had previously been the three estates.
There is now the National Assembly is the embodiment of the will and the sovereignty of the people.
The Bastille has fallen. The first émigrés have fled.
And Louis, who has not fled, is trying to reinvent himself as a constitutional monarch.
But while all this is going on, everything that precipitated the revolution,
so chiefly the fact that there's no money and that the bread price is very high, that hasn't really changed.
Yeah. So there's still an atmosphere of panic and crisis, isn't there?
So here's the thing. Why are the deputies who are in the National Assembly,
why would they spend all their time talking about a declaration of human rights
when you would think their priority would be to be discussing bread supplies or whatever it might be?
Because.
I think that most of the deputies who had assembled at Versailles in May 1789,
say for the Estates General, that then becomes the National Assembly.
I mean, they thought that they had come there to give France a new constitution.
And I think they operate on the assumption that you can't remedy the ills facing France
unless you have set the country on new foundations.
And the Declaration of Rights is an attempt to frame for both the delegates,
themselves, but also for all the people of France,
an understanding of what henceforward will be animating the new France.
Right.
And I think that that is actually an understanding that is turbocharged by the fall of the Bastille.
Because you were saying how the people in the National Assembly are actually perturbed by what happens.
Yeah.
They're unsettled by it.
And actually, I'm right in saying, aren't I, that as the weeks go by,
so during the time they're thinking about this,
the news coming in, not so much from Paris, but from the countryside,
Yeah.
is more.
Alarming than ever, and arguably more alarming than ever before in French history,
because this is the year of what historians call the great fear,
la grande peur, the great fear.
The great fear.
So this is coming in from the provinces.
Yeah.
I mean, I think there's hope as well as fear.
So there's, we've already mentioned him, Arthur Young, this Englishman who's gone on a trip across France.
An ill-timed holiday.
Yeah, an ill-timed trip.
So he, two days before, he went on a trip to Paris.
Before the fall of the Bastille, he is in Lorraine and he meets a peasant woman.
He asks her, you know, how you doing?
And he writes what she said.
It was said at present that something was to be done by some great folks for such poor ones,
but she did not know who nor how, but God send us better because property taxes and
feudal dues are crushing us.
And Arthur Young, as a kind of illustration of the way that the poor are being crushed
by the weight on them, he assumes that this woman must be kind of 60 or 70, but he asks,
and she turns out to be 28.
So, yeah.
Oh no, that's how French people look though, Tom, what can you do?
But then the Bastille falls and that actually, that turns up, it doesn't lessen the temperature
in the countryside.
It actually, you know, it sends it through the roof because people now start, you know,
they hear that one fortress has fallen and they start to attack other citadels of authority,
don't they?
And they're burning the registers and they're smashing their way in.
I think the fall of the Bastille is reported as the fall of feudalism.
And we, again, mentioned this in the previous episode, it's very peasants revolt.
There's this idea that if you as a peasant can burn the registers and the charters that
condemn you to work as a peasant, then you will be free.
And so they start targeting castes, yeah, chateaux and particularly abbeys and monasteries,
which also, you know, as in the days of the peasant revolt, own large tracts of land,
and this brings kind of feudal dues and tithes with them.
So an example of an abbey that gets attacked is one in Burgundy called Senazon, and this
is completely leveled and it belongs to a very distinguished local family, the family
of Talleyrand-Périgord, and the best known member of this family is actually a bishop,
the bishop of the local town of Autun, and he had basically become a bishop because his
nurse had not been looking after him and drops him on the floor and it damages his
foot when he's about three and the foot never heals.
And so he grows up unable to fulfill the military destiny that otherwise would have been his
as a kind of swaggering aristocrat.
And so he has no choice but to go into the church, which is an absolute mismatch between
his talents because he's quite marquis de Sade.
I mean, he's not that bad, but he's a kind of cynic.
He's a free thinker.
He is.
He's done.
Definitely inclined to libertinism.
I think it's fair to say.
Yeah.
But he is unbelievably able, shrewd, kind of cunning operator, kind of almost the embodiment
of the Machiavelli, isn't he?
Yeah, I mean, he's the great survivor.
The great survivor.
So he gets elected as a member of the first estate, so that's the church, to go to Versailles.
And when he's there, rather than kind of bat for the church, he teams up with Mirabeau,
who's the great
spokesman for the third estate.
And they are sat together, kind of working out drafts for the Declaration of the Rights
of Man as news from the provinces is coming in.
And the news is very, very alarming if you have any commitment to the integrity of the
nation.
So the whole country seems to be disintegrating.
And we talked about the importance of rumour and the anxiety of conspiracy in the context
of the Bastille.
This is exactly what's happening in the country.
And there are kind of terrified stories that the aristocrats are deliberately setting out
to starve or poison the poor.
And if that sounds mad, again, this is a staple of plots in the Marquis de Sade's novels.
This idea that aristocrats have nothing better to do than to kind of plot starvation and
ruin for the entire country is clearly part of the kind of the climate of paranoia of
the time.
And even at this stage, there's a sort of...
There's a...
I don't know whether xenophobia is too strong a word, but there's a great fear of foreigners,
isn't there?
That there are foreign armies that are poised to attack at any moment, that there are foreign
sponsored bands of brigands.
People attack foreigners.
They attack Jews.
They're looking for scapegoats.
And this sort of mad paranoia that there's somebody out there, maybe just over the hill,
who's going to attack your town, burn your crops, steal all your food, all of that kind
of stuff.
And so the process of people then forming militias to guard your town.
And so it's a kind of knock-on effect that people are raising militias against the phantoms
of militias.
And so it goes on.
And this is absolutely not what people want.
You know, people are not demanding a kind of the disintegration of the country.
Actually, they want greater control.
They want people who can sort this out and give them bread and give them security.
And basically, what they're trying to do is they're trying to make it so that they don't
even know what they're doing.
And it's going to be an attack on their country.
And so, now, they are Lysa' hardly afraid to attack Hallo, I don't know if they can
And so, what happens is that people are doing this kind of Believable movement, as Lysa'
had said, they're doing this as a sort of threat to the people.
So, it's like, you know, what are we waiting for?
What are we waiting for today?
What are we waiting for in the next week or so?
And so, it's a kind of kind of security.
It's like, what do we want, what are we waiting for?
It's like level two.
No, it's not.
1989. And it's a time when the National Assembly is actually very thinly attended.
It's the evening. And a guy stands up who you mentioned, Dominic, in the previous episode,
the Vicomte de Neu, the guy who comes in and reports the fall of the Bastille to the king.
And he's a man who has a foot in both the kind of the royal and the revolutionary camps.
So his mother is Madame Etiquette, who is the, you know, the guide to Marie Antoinette,
who is always kind of scolding her for breaking the etiquette and so on.
So the upholder, the embodiment of the rules and regulations of the court.
Exactly. But he has served alongside Lafayette, who is his brother-in-law in the American Revolution.
And when Cornwallis surrendered at Yorktown, he had been the official representative of France.
I hate him already.
Right. Well, so he's interestingly positioned.
And so he...
He stands up and he says that the kingdom of France is floating between the complete destruction of society
and a government which would be admired and followed throughout Europe.
So in other words, we have to do something radical or it will be complete anarchy.
And so the radical step he proposes is that all feudal obligations should be abolished,
which, of course, is essentially means that from that point on,
people will not need to go around ransacking chateaus and abbeys.
And the other thing which he...
He proposes in a very kind of offhand manner is that everyone in the kingdom should pay taxes.
And this is precisely the issue that had been inspiring people in the previous year to refuse to accept the king's kind of fiscal solution.
This is the maddest thing, isn't it?
This is the maddest aspect of this whole story.
This sense of, I mean, people talk about, one delegate I see describes it as a moment of patriotic drunkenness.
People throwing their distinctions on the bonfire and saying, yeah, let's all pay tax.
And the madness is this whole situation would not have come about if they had just agreed to pay tax as the king wanted a year or two earlier.
I mean, it is the extent to which they have swung and they're now seized with this almost hysterical, almost paranoid passion.
I mean, it really is one of the great political turnarounds.
Yeah, so Sharma calls it a cult of self-dispossession.
And I mean, I think it is something that would be very recognizable today.
It's people checking.
They're privilege, you know, standing up and saying, I have too much privilege.
I must get rid of it all.
But there's also, I mean, there's kind of tit for tat quality between the, say, the representatives of the church and the aristocracy.
So a bishop stand up and proposes the abolition of all hunting rights.
So essentially from this point on, anyone can just shoot anything that they want.
And so Duke then stands up and says, yeah, fine, but we'll get rid of church tithes.
And by the end of it, I think it's not just feudalism.
That's been jettisoned, but the very notion of privilege itself.
And so William Doyle in the Oxford history of the French Revolution, he says it proved to be the most sweeping and radical legislative session of the whole French Revolution.
And it was all just the event of an evening, a night, people standing up and saying, let's get rid of everything.
All that fuss about the defense of privilege and privilege being part of liberty.
And now in one evening, they're throwing them all away.
Yeah, it's amazing.
And then.
Of course, three weeks later comes the declaration, which is the second kind of monumental moment in this process of legislation.
And you said yes last time that actually the guy who originally proposes it is your mate Lafayette.
An empty headed political dwarf, as the dictionary of the French Revolution calls him.
A dashing representative of Franco-American friendship.
And obviously he's been in America.
He's very close to George Washington.
He has close relations with Thomas Jefferson, who is the American ambassador in Paris at this point.
And so he basically proposes that it be on the American model.
And he thinks, you know, just as the American declaration had joined the various states in America together, he thinks that it will help unify a sundering nation in France.
And it proclaims 17 rights.
And the first of these, men are born and remain free and equal in rights.
Social distinctions may be based.
Only on considerations of the common good.
So that is egalite.
That's the expression of all the feudal privileges that have been jettisoned.
And this, in turn, then defines what the purpose of good governance should be.
The aim of every political association is the preservation of the natural and imprescriptible rights of man.
These rights are liberty, property, safety and resistance to oppression.
With an emphasis there, I think, on the first word, liberte.
Yes.
So that's the second article.
And I think it's very obvious what the target of that article is.
And the third article is.
The third article makes it clear, the principle of any sovereignty lies primarily in the nation, no corporate body, no individual may exercise any authority that does not expressly emanate from it.
So the corporate body is clearly the church and the individual is clearly the king, although neither are actually mentioned.
And no supernatural authority there either.
No supernatural authority, yeah.
But interestingly, the nation, so a new abstract noun, no one questions what the nation might be or says, well, actually, that's quite hard to define.
Well, actually, that's quite hard to define.
But who belongs to the nation?
What does the nation even mean?
Well, the nation is a community joined in the bonds of fraternity.
Yeah.
So we have galate, liberte, fraternity.
They're all they've all been kind of name checked.
And then so that's the kind of the more abstract end of the list.
But what you then have is a whole list of articles that are clearly very, very prescriptively trying to knock away the various.
props of the Ancien Regime.
So Article 9, every man is presumed innocent until he's been declared guilty.
That's targeting the letter to cachet, the way in which the king could just have people arrested and put in prison.
Article 10, no one may be disturbed on account of his opinions, even religious ones, as long as the manifestation of such opinions does not interfere with the established law and order.
So that's targeting the privileged position held by the Catholic Church.
This is in law.
So ever since 1715, the Protestants.
It's been named illegal.
Catholicism had been the only legally permissible faith.
And so it's unsurprising that actually, even the clerics who have cheerfully jettisoned their privileges are very, very upset about this.
And they, it's their opposition that delays the final agreement on this document for about a week.
And then Article 11, the free communication of ideas and opinions is one of the most precious rights of man.
So no more censorship.
Whether that's coming from.
The king or from the church.
So Tom, the question is, I mean, some of these things you, as an Anglo-Saxon, you, you could say, you know, we have quite a lot of this in Britain or in the United States, the new United States of America.
So to what extent do you think this is genuinely, I mean, I can see how you, for a Frenchman, you think this is groundbreaking and a transformative moment in world history, but of course, I mean, there's sort of, as to go back to the, the Margaret Thatcher argument, could you say, well, come on, a lot of this.
This exists already.
What's so special and what's so groundbreaking about all this?
So I, I think it is an absolutely decisive moment in world history.
Uh, and it's, it's decisive because it is, um, an overt rupture with so much that had gone before, and it's a rupture that's happening in the preeminent, you know, intellectual capital of Europe.
Um, but I think it's also, it's also significant as a reiteration.
Of things that had gone before.
So I don't think that the rupture is quite as complete as, um, as people say.
So it's very self-consciously a new beginning.
That's what that, you know, this is the great kind of manifesting, um, principle that governs the whole declaration.
But of course, as you pointed out, the revolutionaries aren't the first to attempt such a thing.
And it's kind of implicit in the declaration because, you know, it's saying that the rights it proclaims are natural, unalienable and sacred.
Then it's, I mean, it's mad to think that they can't have been proclaimed before, or are the French saying, you know, they're the first people to discover them to have noticed them.
Yeah.
And, and then there's the further issue of, you know, is this a, is, is this a document that is targeted at France at a particular moment in its history or are the pretensions it has to, to, to be universal, you know, are they authentic?
Well, that's the, the, the, the nation, if you're talking about that, the nation that, that raises that as a problem, doesn't it?
Because.
Yeah.
Is it, I mean, this is an argument that goes to the core of the French revolution.
Is it universalist or is it, well, it obviously is universalist, but it is also the crucible of nationalism.
It is.
And it's France that invents modern nationalism.
Yeah.
And so there's, there's a massive tension there, which I think will run throughout the revolution and indeed throughout 19th and 20th century history as well.
But what it does very effectively is to provide a kind of legal imprimatur.
For the destruction of the Ancien Regime.
So it is the, it's the kind of, it's the, it's the intellectual parallel to the, the, the demolition of the stones of the Bastille.
So just as the walls of the Bastille are being demolished, the appearance of these words and articles on a piece of paper that then gets passed is doing something similar.
It is eradicating supposedly the taint of absolutism.
So this idea that sovereignty now lies with the nation and not the king.
I mean, this is, this is a massive, massive step and it, the implications for the, what had previously been the two estates, the nobility and the church are obviously also seismic.
So the logical implication is that the nobility should no longer exist.
If they have no privileges, then what's the point of them.
And, you know, basically within, within less than a year.
So, so on the 19th of June, 1790, all hereditary titles are abolished and all the kind of traditional symbols of nobility.
So coats of arms, the kind of the liveries that are worn by servants, you know, people with their own pews in church, all that kind of thing, they all go.
But the, it's, it's the church, I think that actually loses even more because the, that most of the aristocracy have so much.
And of course, property has been guaranteed under the declaration of the rights of man.
So they keep their lands for the church.
It's, it's a much more crippling fact that tithes have been abolished.
So tithes, you know, the, the, the money that is raised to keep the church going, you know, that's gone.
So, so when that happens, or particularly the poor parish, parish clergy have completely lost their source of income.
Yeah.
And the Catholic church.
The church has also been forced to concede complete and total freedom of, of, of worship and thought.
And I think that, that in a way, this is the most, in the context of France, this is the most revolutionary development of all because France, because the church in France is an even older institution than the monarchy it's, it's, it's privileges have been writ very, very large over the course of French history.
I mean, going.
Going back to, well, to the very founding of the monarchy.
So I think two scenes from the reign of Louis the 16th kind of illustrate the way in which even the monarchy stands in the shadow of the antiquity of the church.
So Louis, Louis coronation in June, 1775, massively retro, even though actually he, he, Louis does make sure that Marie Antoinette has her own purpose built toilet, which was very nice.
So, so it's held in RAS where this is the traditional place for, for, for, for Kings to be crowned.
This is the key episode in the life of Joan of Arc where she, she gets to crown the Dauphin there.
But the reason why RAS is, is the place that you go is that in 496, the first Frankish King to convert to Christianity had been crowned there, and he had supposedly been anointed with oil from a kind of.
A flask, a casket that had been brought down by a white dove and Louie standing there being anointed, being crowned had swat.
He, this is his, his oath.
I swear to devote myself sincerely.
And with all my power to annihilating heretics condemned by the church in all lands under my rule.
So there you have everything that the enlightened despise French church kind of doves coming down with oil.
Yeah.
Secretarian hostility to Protestants.
An oath that Louie would undoubtedly have taken enormously seriously.
And as we'll see.
The fact that he is now contravening that oath and what he sees as his, his, his loyalty to the church.
More generally, that is going to have a massive psychological impact on him.
It will.
And then Dominic bookending that at the beginning of his reign, the, the episode that you described in the previous episode where he comes to, to Paris after the fall of the Bastille.
And, um, you know, he goes to the hotel to feel and he.
is given the cocade and oh yeah the cocade yeah by lafayette and this will become form the colors
of the tricolor so white for the color of the monarchy and um blue and red for the city of
paris and why red and blue that's a good question these are the colors of the two saints the two
patrons say two of the patron saints of paris so the blue is for san martin saint martin of tor
man of very humble stock who in the fourth century had risen to become the bishop of tor
and he is famous of course for giving half his cloak to a beggar who had no clothes who you
might describe as a son culotte a man too poor to to buy his own clothes yeah um and san martin
gives him the cloak to to cover him um and the red is for saint denis and saint denis had supposedly
been beheaded um
in the third century on a great hill overlooking paris uh that had then been given the name of mont
martre the mountain of the martyr and from montmartre san denis was supposed to have carried
his head preaching a sermon as he went um he then reaches the he reaches a spot to the north of
paris where he finally dies and a great basilica dedicated to saint denis is raised over it and
this is the french westminster abbey this is where all the kings and queens of france are buried and
it kind of
beautifully exemplifies the historical ironies and tensions of the fact that this cockade that
louis is wearing in his hat it's a symbol of a new order it's the union you know of a patriot king a
constitutional king with his people but it also without most people even thinking about it has
these echoes of a fabulously ancient past and it focuses i think the big question is it possible
actually to have a new beginning that doesn't bear the weight of the old and the new beginning and
it doesn't bear these trace elements of the past right can you have year zero can you authentically
have a year zero or are you inevitably in doing that going to bear the kind of the marks of of the
contamination of the past reaching back you know not just decades but centuries and even millennia
and you know that you can ask the same question about the declaration of the rights of man and
citizen is it a repudiation of the catholic heritage the christian heritage or dominic is it
something more complex is it a reworking of it so when people ask is it is it a bit more complex
they never say no it's actually much simpler have you noticed that they never do that time
i've never because it never is is it episodes so jonathan israel argues that there are there
are difference the enlightenment is this process of it's driven by human reason and scientific
inquiry and all of that kind of thing the skepticism and that it has different phases
and there's something that he calls the radical enlightenment
and what exactly does he how does he distinguish the radical enlightenment so the radical
enlightenment is um overtly hostile to religion uh overtly often overtly hostile to monarchy
so um and because the french revolution will end up bringing down both
it's understandable why people should look to the the the kind of the underground writings of the
enlightenment for inspiration um and you you know there are indisputably figures who do bear the the
markers of that and probably the most famous of them is uh uh an aristocrat inevitably um called
the marquis de condorcet who is um he's a philosopher uh he's a mathematician he's an
economist um and he a a bit like um lavoisier who we talked about in the previous episode he's a
great enthusiast for cleaning up rivers so he kind of it's a kind of fertile sharky-esque quality to
um our overseas citizens won't know that he's done okay right but so fogel sharky is a a campaigner
against pollution in britain's rivers and the marquis and the marquis de condorcet would would
have gone on tremendously well and he's he you know his his hostility to to sewage in rivers
is uh reflective of his hostility to the sewage of superstition and barbarism in public discourse
dominic no one likes the sewage of barbarism do they no well i don't know i've got a slight
soft spot for it i'll be honest and so unsurprisingly when the revolution kicks off
the marquis de condorcet is a huge enthusiast for it and he casts it absolutely as it so often
is to this day as being uh the triumph of progress over superstition and he's very very into the idea
that that what you have to do is dig down deep muster empirical data uh don't rely
on um kind of mad stories about doves bringing down holy oil or anything like that uh you know
that's not going to help in the battle with with ignorance and poverty um christianity is nonsense
um it's objective reason that will provide the inspiration for people in the war against
um all the faults that the ancien regime had embodied um and he sees the duty of the revolution
to scour france and indeed more broadly the world free of the taint of specifically christianity
which he detests so he says he says the christian millennium is an impressive demonstration of what
energetic reactionaries can do to spread superstition demote the intellect prolonged
stagnation secure tyranny degrade man as a reasonable being and thus hold back the march
of mind for centuries oh okay and in saying that he he is echoing um the
the the kind of underground enlightenment philosophers but he is also echoing the
most famous of all the french philosopher of the 18th century who we've already mentioned
who's voltaire the the great wit who had cast the bastille is this terrible uh dungeon he'd written
up about the the man in the iron mask but and is very very i mean he's probably the most famous
writer in 18th century europe he's dead by the time the revolution breaks out but he's is a
master in the history of of the world and he's extremely well-known for his literary work
and and I'm not going to answer his question now but i'm going to answer this because i think
it's really interesting and i'm sure you've had it a few times if you haven't but eric
what's what what you're doing is essentially is you're trying to become a strongman of the
of the world and that is the thing that i've would like to see in my work and in the period
i've spoken about he's never wanted to be a standard leader of the world he's always wanted
to be a standard leader of the world and the world is a composite of him and that he is not
man must hold the christian sect in horror and you know he he is a brilliant brilliant writer
but he's also a brilliant activist and again and again he fixes on examples of tyranny and
oppression that he knows will resonate with the french people so his story about the man in the
iron mask is one of those but there's an even more vivid example because it happens um you know in
his own lifetime so he's picking up on a live injustice and this happened in 1762 and it was
a protestant a huguenot from toulouse in the south of france called jean calin who had been accused
of murdering his own son and he had been convicted um under very dubious circumstances yeah he
obviously didn't kill him yeah obviously well so it turns out yeah and he's broken very horribly
on the wheel and voltaire picks up on this and he says this wasn't
you know he he was broken on the wheel not because he people really thought that he killed
his son but because he was a protestant it's an example of you know religious intolerance at its
brutal worst uh he casts cala as a victim of sectarian persecution and his campaign has such
an impact that in 1764 so only two years after he had died louis the 15th the predecessor of louis
the 16th had actually received cala's family
at versailles and the following year had issued um a posthumous exoneration and you know a a pardon
this is typical of voltaire's campaigning and it makes him um someone that that people not just in
the kind of the radical wing of french opinion but across the whole span of french society comes to
admire very much so in 1778 talleyrand the bishop of hauteur had actually gone and visited voltaire
and he was not allowed to come he'd been in exile in in um geneva he'd come to paris um and talleyrand
had gone to visit voltaire there and voltaire by this point is incredibly old and he has this
brilliant description of voltaire every line of that remarkable countenance is engraved in my
memory i see it now before me the small fiery eyes staring from shrunken sockets not unlike those of
a chameleon yeah it's widely held by enthusiasts for the revolution that the revolution is you know
one of the most important things in the history of the revolution is that voltaire is the father
of it the glorious revolution has been the fruit of his works one of them says um and in fact in 1791
so two years after the fall of the bastille um voltaire's remains are dug up and reinterred in
what is an almost completed church but has been re-consecrated as a temple to liberty the pantheon
yeah the the pantheon the the temple to all the gods and voltaire is buried there amidst kind of
great splendor as one of the kind of the presiding inspirations for the revolution but obviously so
you can see why all this stuff the declaration of the rights of man the legacy of voltaire
you can see why all this would appeal to the marquis de condorcet or somebody who sees
himself as an enlightened free thinker a kind of i mean genuinely a kind of metropolitan intellectual
but obviously most of france is not populated by people like that it's a very rural country
yeah where you know vast millions upon millions of
people work the land they're used to the old ways the old parish church the local cure the the rituals
of the catholic year all of that kind of stuff and they are not reading voltaire they're not so
what on earth did they make of this move from august 1789 onwards the kind of anti-christian
side of the revolution i think lots of them come to be enthused by the spirit of the revolution
i i think they come to accept the revolution on its own terms
i think that's a good point yeah well that's a good point and that's the important thing
is that the more the more devout among catholics come to see the whole revolution basically has
a massive protestant plot and one of the reasons for that is that protestants are actually they
have quite leading roles in the revolution so they're you know the moment that they're allowed
to to kind of practice their religion freely they're busy building churches they're often
quite wealthy so they have the money to hand yeah they're busy joining revolutionary committees in
paris and across the whole of france
1790 a protestant pastor is actually elected president of the national assembly so so
catholics who feel upset about what is happening they look at this and they you know you can find
evidence for thinking well it's it's protestants who are behind it yeah and i think what gives that
what um kind of really puts rocket fuel in that fear is the fact that there are clearly
two massive echoes of the reformation that catholics find quite hard to miss so
the attack on the catholic church again and again is cast as an attack on superstition
very thomas cromwell so the attacks on privilege are often very stridently
anti-clerical and just as in the reformation so now the end of censorship means that
pamphlets
and illustrations can flood everywhere and you don't even need to be able to read to understand
kind of anti-clerical anti-religious pamphlets it's it's it's immediately apparent and anyone
with any familiarity with the reformation would of course immediately see the parallels and just as
luther had kind of staged mocking ceremonies that symbolically uh you know cast contempt on the
papacy
the
the revolution the the church and the aristocracy are both objects of kind of staged managed
processions that make them out to be kind of completely ridiculous you know you get parodies
of the mass you get plays that are very anti-clerical get put on in the in the paris
theaters sponsored by enthusiasts for the uh for the um for the revolution and undoubtedly lots of
people are swayed by this you know they find it very exciting the the the way in which suddenly
they're being allowed to think in ways that they previously had never thought to think
but there are others who find it deeply ups unsettling so that's on the ideological level
but of course the reformation isn't just about ideology it's also about money cash and property
and there is an attack that that kind of builds up from the the abolition of the church's tithes
through the months and years that follow that is actually pretty henry viii
because we've said the the revolution hasn't really improved the fiscal crisis
that had done so much to bring it about france is still basically bankrupt there's no money
so how to plug the gap and you know that's exactly the question that prompted henry viii to end up
dissolving the monasteries and it's the solution that you know the more radical elements in the
national assembly kind of start thinking well you know maybe we could do this because the church
controls so much
yeah i mean they own something like ten percent of the nation as well who's the guy who
who basically proposes this telling you it's talleybrook the bishop of the bishop
of utah but i mean that bishopric is is kind of slightly normal let's slightly slightly so
he does this on the 10th of october so that's a few months after the abolition of tithes
and i think actually to be fair to tell you it's not just the kind of cynical proposal um
because he's saying you know we can take all this land and it can
you know lots of the money can go towards helping the nation's finances but we could also basically
nationalize the church and we could use the money from all these properties to give all the people
in the church a kind of flat fee a flat income yeah and this isn't joseph ii um the emperor the
hapsburg emperor the brother of marie antoinette had come up with a very similar kind of wheeze
and that basically had had gone through um so there are that you know there are elements within
the church you think yeah fine fair enough and obviously the radical elements so mirabeau and all
his his his pals they think it's a brilliant idea and they take it to the national assembly the vast
majority of people in the national assembly aren't clergy so they think it's brilliant as well and
the proposal is voted through but it has to be said that for obvious reasons most of the clergy
really
hate it because the implication is that they will now be kind of moral functionaries
state employees and this isn't the sense they have of their invocation at all and isn't this
interesting that uh when we were talking about the estates general which becomes the national
assembly we were saying that you know some of the big drivers of reform
are the parish priests who are the poorest people there who are the closest to ordinary
frenchmen who are often seized with a real idealism because they're the
first to join the the states general aren't they it's a few poor parish priests yeah they're to
go and join the third estate and become the national assembly but within months a wedge
is being driven between the revolution and probably the majority of ordinary priests
even those who end up signing up to it are very very conflicted about it
i think there are the the poorest priests are the other ones the likeliest to side with this
because they stand to benefit but obviously there are there are you know any any priest with with a
relatively higher income is going to have to take a pay cut and the people who are really in the
crosshairs are other monks and the nuns just as they were in in henry viii's reformation
because first they've been deprived of their income and now they're deprived of their lands
and the the corollary of this is at exactly as in henry viii's time so on the 13th of february
all monasteries and convents except those who who are kind of devoted to um charitable work are
officially designed
well we can't really say that they're actually
of time that it's been become quite a bit of a shared thing it's been evolved and it's it's
forbidden people to start taking monastic boughs or or or vow in a conventional now
and nuns have been absolute staples of these kind of pornographic tracts that we've been talking
about quite a lot not because we're prurient but because they they they condition how people
see the establishment in quite a fundamental way um and there is a feeling among enthusiasts for
the enlightenment that there is in you know they are useless yeah you contribute nothing to society
they need to be turned into useful citizens and so march and april 1790 you get all these kind of
bands of of patriots with their cockades and their revolutionary sashes turning up and doing
a going full thomas cromwell kind of chucking the the monks and the nuns out so i you can see why by
the summer of 1790 i think that there is a kind of increasing sense of alienation um in the church
from the revolution you know this is what not what the the abbey abbe de ca thought that he was
he was encouraging
um
he first proposed um dissolving the the three estates into a single national assembly yeah in
talleyrand's own sea of autant you start getting letters from his his you know his flock kind of
saying he's an absolute traitor he's a judas what you know what is he up to um but it's not just in
no time it's across the whole of france you get priests who you know they don't want to dissolve
their sense of themselves as belonging to god's church and to just be a part of the church and
become the equivalent of kind of magistrates or or officers in the army civil servants um you know
they the whole point of being a priest is that their primary loyalty is not to the the patry not
to the nation it is to god there you have that tension the universalism and the nationalism
yet again but talking of universalism i mean the universe you know catholicos means universal and
the head of the universal church is the pope so that is the head of the church not the the national
assembly and the pope is saying basically i you know i'm not going to put up with this this kind
of revolutionary stuff yeah um so he in secret the pope in rome uh pious the sixth he starts to
condemn the declaration of the rights of man and all the policies that are being pursued in france
on on on kind of relations to the church and this obviously sets up a kind of massive tension within
the church and by extension within the vast mass of the french people um not least because the
national assembly rather than you know trying to arrive at an accommodation with the papacy and
with the church just doubles down you know they're they're not in a mood to negotiate with
superstition and absolutism you know they're not going to allow privilege to to to flourish and so
they feel we need to find a supply of committed
citizens
and priests the church as it stands is not doing that so we need to um to push things forward and
their solution in july 1790 is to draw up what they call the civil constitution of the clergy
and by the tenets of this priests and bishops are to be elected and of course the electorate by this
point would include protestants it would include jews it would include self-professed atheists and
they will effectively you know it's like electing a jp or something um and once they have been
elected everyone who is going to take up his position you know as a as a kind of state priest
citizen priest will be obliged to swear an oath of loyalty to the nation and to its laws and
i think that to most people in the national assembly this doesn't seem a big deal at all
it's a kind of it's it's you know it's a process of legislative tide
up but to priests to lots of priests it's a source of complete agony because they they have now been
put in the position that lots of them have been struggling to avoid where they have to choose
between swearing this oath yeah the oath to the revolution or staying true to the authority of
the pope of the church of god it's massive moments isn't it it's a really really invidious choice
and you know just just as the uh the declaration of the rights of man tends not to have perhaps
the resonance in in english-speaking countries that that it certainly does in france so likewise
this this the civil constitution of the clergy i i think if you said you know what's the key moment
in the french revolution i certainly wouldn't have said this no but it's amazing when you read
histories of the revolution you know english histories of the revolution again and again
historians point to this
as being the key moment that fractures the revolution fractures any sense of kind of
national harmony so this is simon sharma the civil constitution was not simply another piece
of institutional legislation it was the beginning of a holy war uh william doyle in the oxford
history of the french revolution the french revolution had many turning points but the
oath of the clergy was unquestionably one of them if not the greatest um and peter mcfee and his
liberty or death book on the french revolution the oath fractured both the
church and the revolution yeah i remember doing this a-level tom and the civil constitution the
clergy i regarded as incredibly boring and dry and everybody kind of skipped it and because we
couldn't wait to get onto the terror but um i think you're quite right to emphasize it because
this does feel like the moment when what has been kind of one process carrying a lot of people along
with it when it really divides and it becomes i mean that tension has always been there and that
sense of an incipient kind of division between us and them yeah between the people who are
on the side of the patria or the nation and those people who are traitors or conspirators but this
is the moment that drives a lot of people who might otherwise have gone along with the revolution
against it because they are being asked to rip up everything they held not just dear but everything
they held sacred and a lot of people just will not do that and i think you know i think there
are the faintest echoes of the brexit referendum for us in britain right because effectively it
comes to serve
as a referendum because priests obviously pay attention to what their flock think
um and the the the the the division is quite kind of brexit-like so 54
of priests end up taking the oath which means that 46 don't yeah and there are very clear geographical
divisions so in paris they're taking is very high in the regions around paris um in provence is very
high um
but in the in the countryside and particularly in the west
it's essentially you have what has now emerged as a counter-revolutionary block
and you have people who are defining themselves as citizens and you have people who are defining
themselves as as christians as communities of of souls yeah and both sides come to increasingly
cast the other side in the direction of the revolution and so there's big gaps in the
darkest possible light so enthusiasts for revolution see the see see their opponents as
as people who are clinging on to superstition and and all kind of privilege and all kinds of things
like that whereas enthusiasts for priests who've taken the oath see the revolutionaries as you know
bloodthirsty fanatics who are destroying everything that has made their life precious and it's the
moment where you you get counter-revolution as the as as the the kind of the the opposite to
revolution which up until that point i think you hadn't have and it poses the question of could it
have been different i mean might the revolution have been able to take the vast mass of of catholic
citizens with them and there's a kind of i i know of no better
kind of
t
teaser for that question than a famous painting which was it was done in um 1789 in the wake of
the the drawing of the declaration of the rights of man by a painter called jean-jacques francois
le barbier who had actually been a court painter to louis the 16th and in the wake of the signing
the declaration he is employed to give it a visual representation so he gives all the kind of the
favorite symbols so there's you know broken chains and there's a liberty cap and there's
great
a sonic eye gazing down but the thing that's striking about the the portrayal of the declaration
itself is that it is written as though it is carved onto stone tablets yeah and the stone
tablets of course are an echo of the tablets that were given to moses on mount sinai which is the
kind of the definitive expression of divine revelation not of human law and of course a
a prefiguring tom an important and interesting prefiguring of um ed milliband's stone
tablets in 2015. yeah so the echoes of the french revolution reverberate everywhere when le barbier
is doing that what is he doing is he is he saying it's possible to synthesize the bible and the
enlightenment yeah you don't need to choose between them the two can merge and if that's
what he's saying i mean it's not completely mad because actually it's it's very clear when you
look at the enlightenment that a lot of the values that the enlightenment assumes are universal that
would accept are actually bred from deeply christian assumptions i mean people who've
listened to this podcast regularly will be aware if i ever heard you use that phrase before and
you should have a tom holland generator you just press a button and it says bread of deeply
christian assumptions but just to give an example so so voltaire gone his his horror at the fate of
jean calin why is he so upset by this why is he upset by the the the torture to death of an
innocent man or an instrument of torture it clearly reflects kind of deep psychological
response to the figure of christ that voltaire would have absorbed as a child i think maybe or
maybe he just doesn't like people being broken on the wheel by torture i mean is that not possible
but there you're assuming that that's something instinctively that people react against i mean i
think the the evidence suggests contrary wise i think people have put you know plenty of societies
have been perfectly happy with that and calla himself on the wheel i should add kind of makes
this parallel explicit
i die innocent i do not pity myself jesus christ who was innocent died for me by even more cruel
torments and i think what what kind of brings this home is the fact that calla is exonerated
by the french king you know who the anointed king louis the 15th and he's he's exonerated not
because louis the 15th has become an enlightenment philosoph and not because the vast mass of people
in france who feel sympathy for color have become enlightenment philosoph
and and and in sympathy with voltaire's skepticism but because they see voltaire's campaign as being
entirely concordant with christian principles so just to quote um david bien who wrote a brilliant
book on the cal affair the view that the impact of the enlightenment polarized french thought
creating two large mutually suspicious groups one clerical and the other anti-clerical is to read
back the developments of the revolution where it definitely does happen into a period when they
simply were not present
you know we talked about the role that priests play in the early weeks and months of the revolution
um and at the bastille you know this storming of of of a place dank with chains if the stories are
to be believed and the funerals that are given for those who had taken part in the storming of
the bastille the text that is preached by the archbishop of paris comes from paul you my brothers
were called to be free and you were called to be free and you were called to be free and you were
called to be free and you were called to be free and you were called to be free and this is a sentiment
and this is a sentiment that is perfectly in tune with the call to liberty yeah in the in the in the
revolution so tom are you effectively saying and and some people listeners may consider this the
whole the classic holland gambit that the the ideological struggle within the french revolution
of a french of revolutionaries against counter-revolutionaries is basically a
struggle between two different kinds of of of christians i am basically
saying that and it's it's about the attempt i think of the the the revolution to appropriate
much of its inheritance from the christian past and i think that's the other way of interpreting
le berbier's picture is that it's not in any way saying that um that the bible and the enlightenment
you know christ and voltaire can be synthesized it's saying that the a revolutionary revolution
reorder has to appropriate what it can of previous revolutionary orders yeah and the truth is that
there is something distinctive i think about european society in the west that reaches right
the way back beyond the reformation back to the 11th century when europe's primal revolution
happens where you have um basically you know it's it's the catholic church that is directing it you
have you have a pope who humbles kings the humbling of the pope who humbles kings the humbling of the
kings is a vital part of the dynamics of what is going on in the 11th century you have an emperor
kneeling in the snow before a pope you have a notion that society itself can be born again
can be bred anew can be washed in blood and emerge as something new and it creates a kind of division
within society that by the by the time of the revolution has been framed as being religious
and secular yeah and of course the the you know the catholic church is the universal church
so that instinct on the part of the revolutionaries to preach universalism
is a highly deeply christian one and finally just on the the the declaration that we began
with the declaration of human rights where did the idea of human rights come from you know then
if they're universal they are not evident in antiquity they are not evident in parts of the
world beyond glassing latin christendom they emerge in the 12th century as a product of the
the kind of the the the cultural ferment of that first revolution um in in italy in the 12th century
and that's where they come from so if the revolution is to proclaim that these are universal
and that the revolution embodies them it needs to utterly incinerate and obliterate the memory
of that i think that what the revolution demonstrates is actually that the one thing
a revolutionary hates more than a reactionary is a rival revolutionary and i think the hostility
between the revolution as it will emerge over the course of the period that we've been talking
about so into the into the period of the terror is that the hostility of the revolution towards
the catholic church is similar towards it's similar to the hostility that the the protestant
reformers felt towards the papacy it's kind of a rival church it's it's it's a rival yes yeah
exactly interesting interesting the holland gambit and never
more brilliantly deployed tom than i than just now um so all of that lies ahead because we will
get to the terror and the the the sort of civil war within the revolution but but obviously right from
the start to go back to the declaration of human rights that was what august 1789 and right from
that point louis and marianne and the people who have not fled who are still around them they don't
like this kind of stuff at all of course not because it has implications for the monarchy as
so louis published a response to the declaration in september and he and he said he kind of said
yeah i love the spirit of it great and then he went through all the specifics and said don't
agree with that yeah so like the serbian reply to the austrian ultimatum very good
yes very good and and i think for me the obvious problem that they have with their constitution
building and their desire to to set france on a new on a new sort of even keel is that they
have a huge hole at the center of their constitution which is the king because they're
they've they've been talking about a british-style constitutional monarchy they have yeah um but
is louis gonna play that part i mean is he ever psychologically ready and particularly once the
church which he has sworn an oath to uphold once that comes into the kind of firing line
i don't think he's ever you were saying is there ever a way they can this can be all be reconciled
i don't think he's ever gonna right gonna adjust himself to this um to this new world and obviously
we're gonna get back to the narrative because in just a few weeks after that after his response
to the declaration that tension will reach a climax won't it with one of the most um dramatic
exciting tragic episodes of the entire revolution and that's what we're doing tomorrow tom it is
it's the march the women's march on versailles oh very exciting so we'll be looking at that and
we'll be looking the way in which the revolution has to work out what it's going to do about
the monarchy so we will be back with that tomorrow adam and stuff au revoir